I'll explain Mr. Rochester did, on a future occasion, explain it.
It was one afternoon, when he chanced to meet me and Adele in the grounds.
And while she played with pilot and her shuttle cock, he asked me to walk up and
down a long beach avenue within sight of her.
He then said that she was the daughter of a French opera dancer, Selene Verance,
towards whom he had once cherished what he called a grand pasion.
This passion, Selene had professed a return with even superior ade.
He thought himself her idol, ugly as he was.
He believed, as he said, that she preferred his tile
d'athlete to the elegance of the Apollo Belvedere.
And Miss Eyre, so much was I flattered by this preference of the Gallic silt for her
British gnome, that I installed her in and hotel, gave her a complete establishment
of servants, a carriage, cashmiers, diamonds, don'tels, etc.
In short, I began the process of ruining myself
in the received style, like any other spoonie.
I had not, it seems, the originality to chalk out a new road to shame and
destruction, but trod the old track with stupid
exactness not deviate an inch from the beaten centre.
I had, as I deserved to have, the fate of all other spoonies.
Happening to call one evening when Selene did not expect me, I found her out.
But it was a warm night, and I was tired with strolling through Paris, so I sat
down in her boudoir, happy to breathe the air consecrated so lately by her presence.
No, I exaggerate, I never thought there was any consecrating virtue about her.
It was rather a sort of pastel perfume she had left, a scent of musk and amber,
than an odour of sanctity.
I was just beginning to stifle with the fumes of conservatory flowers and
sprinkled essences, when I before myself to
open the window and step out onto the balcony.
It was moonlight and gaslight besides, and very still and serene.
The balcony was furnished with a chair or two.
I sat down and took out a cigar.
I will take one now if you will excuse me.
Here in pseudopause, filled up by the producing and lighting of a cigar,
having placed it to his lips, and breathed a trail of
Havana incense on the freezing and sunless air he went on.
I liked bonbon too in those days miss air, and I was croquant, overlook the barbarism.
Croquant chocolate confetes, and smoking alternately, watching meantime the ecu
-pages that rolled along the fashionable streets, towards the neighbouring opera
house, when in an elegant, close carriage drawn by a beautiful pair of English
horses, and distinctly seen in the brilliant city-night, I recognised the voittour.
I had given Celine, she was returning.
Of course my heart thumped with impatience against the iron rails I lent upon.
The carriage stopped as I had expected at the hotel door my flame, that is the very
word for an opera in a marata, a lighted.
Though muffin a cloak, an unnecessary incumbrance by the by, on so warm a June
evening, I knew her instantly by her little foot, seen peeping from the skirt
of her dress, as she skipped from the carriage step.
Bending over the balcony, I was about to murmur a mournage, in a tone, of course,
which should be audible to the ear of love alone, when a figure jumped from the
carriage after her, cloaked also, but that was a spurred heel, which had
wrung on the pavement, and that was a hatched head, which
now passed under the arched port kosher of the hotel.
You never felt jealousy, did you miss air?
Of course not.
I need not ask you, because you never felt love.
You have both sentiments yet to experience.
Your soul sleeps.
The shock is yet to be given, which shall wake in it.
You think all existence lapses in as choir to flow, as that in which your youth has
hitherto slid away, floating on with closed eyes and muffled ears.
You neither see the rocks bristling not far off in the bed of the flood,
nor hear the breakers boil at their base.
But I tell you, and you may mark my words, you will come someday to a craggy pass in
the channel, where the whole of life's stream will
be broken up into whirl and tumult, foam and noise.
Either you will be dashed to atoms on crag points, or lifted up and born on by some
master wave into a calmer current, as I am now.
I like this day.
I like that sky of steel.
I like the sternness and stillness of the world under this frost.
I like Thornfield.
It's antiquity, it's retirement, it's old crotries and thorn trees,
it's gray facade and lines of dark windows reflecting that metal wellkin,
and yet how long have I abhorred the very thought of it,
shunned it like a great plague house, how I do still abhor.
He ground his teeth and was silent, he arrested his
step and struck his boot against the hard ground.
Some hated thought seemed to have him in its grip,
and to hold him so tightly that he could not advance.
We were ascending the avenue when he thus paused, the hall was before us.
Lifting his eye to its battlements, he cast over
them a glare such as I never saw before or since.
Pain, shame, ire, impatience, disgust, detestation seemed momentarily to hold a
quivering conflict in the large pupil dilating under his ebony brow.
Wild was the wrestle, which should be paramount,
but another feeling rose and triumphed.
Something hard and cynical, self-willed and resolute.
It settled his passion and petrified his countenance.
He went on.
During the moment I was silent, miss air.
I was arranging a point with my destiny.
She stood there by that beach-trunk, a hag like one of those who appeared to
Macbeth on the heath of forest.
You like Thornfield?
She said, lifting her finger, and then she wrote in the air a memento, which ran in
lured, hieroglyphics all along the housefront,
between the upper and lower row of windows.
Like it if you can, like it if you dare.
I will like it, said I, I dare like it, and he subjoined moodily.
I will keep my word, I will break obstacles to happiness, to goodness,
yes goodness, I wish to be a better man than I have been, than I am.
As Job's Leviathan broke the spear, the dart, and the habition, hindrances,
which others count as iron and brass, I will esteem but straw and rotten wood.
Adele here ran before him with her shuttlecock.
Away, he cried harshly, keep at a distance child, or go into Sufi.
Continuing then, to pursue his walk in silence, I ventured
to recall him to the point whence he had abruptly diverged.
Did you leave the balcony, sir, I asked, when Mamazelle Varens entered.
I almost expected a rebuff for this hardly well-timed question, but on the contrary,
waking out of his scowling abstraction, he turned his eyes towards me.
And the shade seemed to clear off his brow.
Oh, I had forgotten Selene.
Well, to resume.
When I saw my charmer thus come in, accompanied by a cavalier, I seemed to
hear a hiss and the green snake of jealousy, rising on undulating coils from
the moonlit balcony, glided within my waistcoat,
and ate its way in two minutes to my heart's core.
Strange, he exclaimed, suddenly starting again from the point.
Strange that I should choose you for the confidant of all this young lady.
Passing strange that you should listen to me quietly, as if it were the most usual
thing in the world for a man like me to tell stories of his
opera mistresses to acquaint inexperienced girl like you.
But the last singularity explains the first, as I intimated once before.
You, with your gravity, considerateness and
caution, were made to be the recipient of secrets.
Besides, I know what sort of a mind I have placed in communication with my own.
I know it is one not liable to take infection.
It is a peculiar mind.
It is a unique one.
Happily, I do not mean to harm it, but if I did, it would not take harm from me.
The more you and I converse the better, for while I cannot blight you,
you may refresh me.
After this digression, he proceeded.
I remained in the balcony.
They will come to her boudoir no doubt, thought I, let me prepare an ambush.
So putting my hand in through the open window, I drew the curtain over it,
leaving only an opening through which I could take observations.
Then I closed the casement, all but a chink, just wide
enough to furnish an outlet to lovers whispered vows.
Then I stole back to my chair, and as I resumed it, the pair came in.
My eye was quickly at the aperture.
Selene's chamber-made entered, little lamp, left it on the table, and withdrew.
The couple with us revealed to me clearly, both
removed their cloaks, and there was the variance.
Shining in satin and jewels, my gifts of course, and there was her companion in an
officer's uniform, and I knew him for a young Rueh of a Vicente, a brainless and
vicious youth, whom I had sometimes met in society, and had
never thought of hating because I despised him so absolutely.
On recognizing him, the fang of the snake jealousy was instantly broken,
because at the same moment, my love for Selene sank under an extinguisher,
a woman who could betray me for such a rival was not worth contending for.
She deserved only scorn, less, however, than I, who had been her dupe.
They began to talk.
Their conversation eased me completely, frivolous, mercenary, heartless,
and senseless.
It was rather calculated to weary than in rage a listener.
A card of mine lay on the table, this being perceived brought my name under discussion.
Neither of them possessed energy or wit to belabor me soundly, but they insulted me
as causally as they could in their little way, especially Selene, who even waxed
rather brilliant on my personal defects, deformities she termed them.
Now it had been her custom to launch out into fervent admiration of what she called
my butemail, wherein she differed diametrically from you, who told me point
blank at the second interview, that you did not think me handsome.
The contrast struck me at the time, and Adele here came running up again.
Monsieur, John has just been to say that your agent has called and wishes to see you.
Ah, in that case I must abridge.
Opening the window, I walked in upon them, liberated Selene from my protection,
gave her notice to vacate her hotel, offered her a purse for immediate
exigencies, disregarded screams, hysterics, prayers, protestations,
convulsions, made an appointment with the I had the pleasure of encountering him,
left a bullet in one of his poor etiolated arms, feeble as the wing of a chicken in
the pip, and then thought I had done with the whole crew.
But unluckily the varen's six months before had given me this filet Adele,
who she affirmed was my daughter, and perhaps she may be, though I see no
proofs of such grim paternity written in her countenance.
Pilate is more like me than she.
Some years after I had broken with the mother, she abandoned
her child and ran away to Italy with a musician or singer.
I acknowledged no natural claim on Adele's part to be supported
by me, nor do I now acknowledge any, for I am not her father.
But hearing that she was quite destitute, Iean took the poor thing out of the slime
and mud of Paris and transplanted it here to grow up
clean in the wholesome soil of an English country garden.
Mrs Fairfax found you to train it, but now you know that it is the
illegitimate offspring of a French opera girl.
You will perhaps think differently of your post and protégé.
You will be coming to me someday with notice that you have found another place,
that you beg me to look out for a new governess, etc.
Eh?
No.
Adele is not answerable for either her mother's faults or yours.
I have a regard for her.
And now that I know she is, in a sense, parentless, forsaken by her mother and
disowned by you, sir, I shall cling closer to her than before.
How could I possibly prefer the spoiled pet of a wealthy family who would hate her
governess as a nuisance, to a lonely little orphan who leans towards her as a friend?
Oh, that is the light in which you view it.
Well, I must go in now, and you too, it darkens.
But I stayed out a few minutes longer with Adele and pilot, ran a race with her,
and played a game of battle-door and shuttlecock.
When we went in, and I had removed her bonnet and coat, I took her on my knee,
kept her there an hour, allowing her to prattle as she liked, not rebuking even
some little freedoms and trivialities into which she was apt to stray when much
noticed, and which betrayed in her a superficiality of character inherited
probably from her mother, hardly congenial to an English mind.
Still, she had her merits, and I was disposed to
appreciate all that was good in her, to the utmost.
I sought in her countenance and features a likeness to Mr. Rochester, but found none,
no trait, no turn of expression announced relationship.
It was a pity, if she could but have been proved
to resemble him, he would have thought more of her.
It was not till after I had withdrawn to my own chamber for the night, that I
steadily reviewed the tale Mr. Rochester had told me.
As he had said, there was probably nothing at all
extraordinary in the substance of the narrative itself.
A wealthy Englishman's passion for a French dancer and her treachery to him,
where every day matters enough, no doubt, in society.
But there was something decidedly strange in the paroxysm of emotion, which had
suddenly seized him, when he was in the act of expressing the present contentment
of his mood, and his newly revived pleasure in the old hall and its environs.
I meditated wonderingly on this incident, but gradually
quitting it as I found it for the present inexplicable.
I turned to the consideration of my master's manner to myself.
The confidence he had thought fit to reposing me seemed a tribute to my discretion.
I regarded and accepted it as such.
His deportment had now for some weeks been more uniform towards me than at the first.
I never seemed in his way.
He did not take fits of chilling hotur.
When he met me unexpectedly, the encounter seemed welcome.
He had always a word and sometimes a smile for me.
When summoned by formal invitation to his presence, I was honoured by a cordiality
of reception that made me feel I really possessed the power to amuse him.
And that these evening conferences were sought
as much for his pleasure as for my benefit.
I indeed talked comparatively little, but I heard him talk with relish.
It was his nature to be communicative.
He liked to open to a mind unequainted with
the world, glimpses of its scenes and ways.
I do not mean its corrupt scenes and wicked ways, but such has derived their
interest from the great scale on which they were acted,
the strange novelty by which they were characterized.
And I had a keen delight in receiving the new ideas he offered, in imagining the new
pictures he portrayed, and following him in thought through the new regions he
disclosed, never startled or troubled by one noxious illusion.
The ease of his manner freed me from painful restraint, the friendly frankness,
as correct as cordial, with which he treated me, drew me to him.
I felt at times as if he were my relation rather than my master, yet he was
imperious sometimes still, but I did not mind that.
I saw it was his way.
So happy, so gratified did I become with this new interest added to life,
that I ceased to pine after kindred.
My thin, present destiny seemed to enlarge.
The blanks of existence were filled up.
My bodily health improved.
I gathered flesh and strength.
And was Mr. Rochester now ugly in my eyes?
No, reader.
Gratitude, and many associations, all pleasurable and genial, made his face
the object I best like to see, his presence in a
room was more cheering than the brightest fire.
Yet I had not forgotten his faults.
Indeed, I could not, for he brought them frequently before me.
He was proud, sardonic, harsh, to inferiority of every description.
In my secret soul, I knew that his great kindness to
me was balanced by unjust severity to many others.
He was moody too, unaccountably so.
I more than once, when sent for to read to him, found him sitting in his library
alone with his head bent on his folded arms.
And when he looked up, a morose, almost a malignant scowl blackened his features.
But I believed that his moodyness, his harshness and his former faults of
morality, I say, former, for now he seemed corrected
of them, had their source in some cruel cross of fate.
I believed he was naturally a man of better tendencies, higher principles,
and purer tastes than such as circumstances had
developed, education instilled, or destiny encouraged.
I thought there were excellent materials in him, though for
the present they hung together somewhat spoiled and tangled.
I cannot deny that I grieved for his grief, whatever
that was, and would have given much to assuage it.
Though I had now extinguished my candle and was laid down in bed, I could not
sleep for thinking of his look when he paused in the avenue, and told how his
destiny had risen up before him, and dared him to be happy at Thornfield.
Why not, I asked myself?
What alienates him from the house?
Will he leave it again soon?
Mrs. Fairfax said he seldom stayed here longer than a fortnight at a time,
and he has now been resident eight weeks.
If he does go, the change will be doleful.
Suppose he should be absent spring, summer and
autumn, how joyless sunshine and fine days will seem.
I hardly know whether I had slept or not after this musing.
At any rate, I started wide awake on hearing a vague murmur, peculiar and
legubrious, which sounded I thought just above me.
I wished I had kept my candle burning, the night
was drearily dark, my spirits were depressed.
I rose and sat up in bed, listening.
The sound was hushed, eee.
I tried again to sleep, but my heartbeat anxiously, my inward tranquility was broken.
The clock, far down in the hall, struck two.
Just then it seemed my chamber door was touched, as if fingers had swept the
panels and groping away along the dark I was chilled with fear.
All at once I remembered that it might be pilot, who, when the kitchen door chance
to be left open, not unfrequently found his way up to the threshold of Mr.
Rochester's chamber, I had seen him lying there myself in the mornings.
The idea calmed me somewhat.
I lay down.
Silence composes the nerves.
And as an unbroken hush now rained again through the
whole house, I began to feel the return of slumber.
But it was not faded that I should sleep that night.
A dream had scarcely approached my ear, when it fled a
frighted, scared by a marrow -freezing incident enough.
This was a demonic laugh, low suppressed and deep.
Uttered as it seemed at the very keyhole of my chamber door.
The head of my bed was near the door, and I thought at first the goblin laugher
stood at my bedside, or rather crouched by my pillow, but I rose, looked around,
and could see nothing.
While as I still gazed, the unnatural sound was
reiterated, and I knew it came from behind the panels.
My first impulse was to rise and fasten the bolt.
My next, again to cry out, who is there?
Something gurgled and moaned.
Airlong steps retreated up the gallery towards the third story staircase.
A door had lately been made to shut in that staircase.
I heard it open and close, and all was still.
Was that grace pool?
And is she possessed with a devil?
Thought I.
Impossible now to remain longer by myself.
I must go to my frock and a shawl.
I withdrew the bolt and opened the door with a trembling hand.
There was a candle burning just outside, and on the matting in the gallery.
I was surprised at this circumstance, but still more was I amazed to perceive
the air quite dim as if filled with smoke, and while looking to the right hand and
left, to find once these blue wreaths issued, I
became further aware of a strong smell of burning.
Something creaked.
It was a door, a jar, and that door was Mr. Rochester's,
and the smoke rushed in a cloud from thence.
I thought no more of Mrs. Fairfax.
I thought no more of grace pool, or the
laugh, in an instant I was within the chamber.
Tongues of flame darted around the bed, the curtains were on fire.
In the midst of blaze and vapor, Mr. Rochester
lay stretched motionless in deep sleep.
Wake!
I cried.
I shook him, but he only murmured and turned.
The smoke had stupified him.
Not a moment could be lost.
The very sheets were kindling, I rushed to his basin and you were.
Fortunately, one was wide and the other deep, and both were filled with water.
I heaved them up, deluged the bed in its occupant, flew back to my own room,
brought my own water jug, baptized the couch of fresh, and by God's aid,
succeeded in extinguishing the flames which were devouring it.
The hiss of the quenched element, the breakage of a picture which I flung
from my hand when I had emptied it, and above all, the splash of the shower
-bath I had liberally bestowed, roused Mr. Rochester at last.
Though it was now dark, I knew he was awake, because I heard him culminating
strange enathomers at finding himself lying in a pool of water.
Is there a flood?
He cried.
No, sir, I answered, but there has been a fire.
Get up, do you are quenched now, I will fetch you a candle.
In the name of all the elves in Christendom, is that Jane Eyre, he demanded?
What have you done with me which sorceress?
Who is in the room besides you?
Have you plotted to drown me?
I will fetch you a candle, sir.
And in heaven's name, get up.
Somebody has plotted something, you cannot too soon find out who and what it is.
There, I am up now.
But at your peril, you fetch a candle yet?
Wait two minutes till I get into some dry garments if any dry there be.
Yes, here is my dressing gown, now run.
I did run.
I brought the candle which still remained in the gallery.
He took it from my hand, held it up, and surveyed the bed, all blackened and
scorched, the sheets drenched, the carpet round, swimming in water.
What is it?
And who did it?
He asked.
I briefly related to him what had transpired.
The strange laugh I had heard in the gallery, the step ascending to the third
story, the smoke, the smell of fire, which had conducted me to his room.
In what state I had found matters there, and how I had
deluged him with all the water I could lay hands on.
He listened very gravely.
His face, as I went on, expressed more concern than astonishment.
He did not immediately speak when I had concluded.
Shall I call Mrs. Fairfax?
I asked.
Mrs. Fairfax, no!
What the juice would you call her for?
What can she do?
Let her sleep unmolested.
Then I will fetch Leah and wake John and his wife.
Not at all.
Just be still.
You have a shawl on.
If you are not warm enough, you may take my cloak yonder.
Wrap it about you and sit down in the armchair.
There, I will put it on.
Now place your feet on the stool to keep them out of the wet.
I'm going to leave you a few minutes.
I shall take the candle.
Remain where you are till I return.
Be as still as a mouse.
I must pay a visit to the second story.
Don't move.
Remember or call anyone.
He went.
I watched the light withdraw.
He passed up the gallery very softly, unclosed the staircase door with as little
noise as possible, shut it after him, and the last ray vanished.
I was left in total darkness.
I listened for some noise, but heard nothing.
A very long time elapsed.
I grew weary.
It was cold, in spite of the cloak.
And then I did not see the use of staying, as I was not to rouse the house.
I was on the point of risking Mr. Rochester's displeasure by disobeying his
orders, when the light once more gleamed dimly on the gallery
wall, and I heard his unshawed feet tread the matting.
I hope it is he, thought I, and not something worse.
He re-entered, pale, and very gloomy.
I have found it all out, said he, setting his candle down on the washstand.
It is as I thought.
How, sir, he made no reply, but stood with his arms folded, looking on the ground.
At the end of a few minutes, he inquired in rather a peculiar tone.
I forget whether you said you saw anything when you opened your chamber door.
No, sir, only the candlestick on the ground.
But you heard an odd laugh.
You have heard that laugh before, I should think, or something like it?
Yes, sir.
There is a woman who sows here called Grace Pool.
She laughs in that way.
She is a singular person.
Just so, Grace Pool, you have guessed it.
She is, as you say, singular, very.
Well, I shall reflect on the subject.
Meantime, I am glad that you are the only person, besides myself,
acquainted with the precise details of tonight s incident.
You are no talking fool.
Say nothing about it.
I will turn to your own room.
I shall do very well on the sofa in the library for the rest of the night.
It is near four, in two hours the servants will be up.
Good night, then, sir, said I, departing.
He seemed surprised, very inconsistently so, as he had just told me to go.
What?
He exclaimed.
Are you quitting me already and in that way?
You said I might go, sir.
But not without taking leave.
Not without a word or two of acknowledgement and good will.
Not in short, in that brief, dry fashion.
Why, you have saved my life, snatched me from a horrible and excruciating death,
and you walk past me as if we were mutual strangers, at least shake hands.
He held out his hand.
I gave him mine.
He took it first in one, then in both his own.
You have saved my life.
I have a pleasure in owing you so immense a debt.
I cannot say more.
Nothing else that has been would have been tolerable to
me in the character of creditor for such an obligation.
But you, it is different.
I feel your benefits no burden, Jane.
He paused.
Gazed at me.
Words almost visible trembled on his lips, but his voice was checked.
Good night again, sir.
There is no debt, benefit, burden, obligation in the case.
I knew he continued.
You would do me good in some way at some time.
I saw it in your eyes when I first beheld you.
Their expression and smile did not.
Again, he stopped.
Did not.
He proceeded hastily.
Strike delight to my very most heart so for nothing.
People talk of natural sympathies.
I have heard of good genie.
There are grains of truth in the wildest fable.
My cherished preserver, good night.
Strange energy was in his voice.
Strange fire in his look.
I'm glad I happened to be awake, I said.
And then I was going.
What?
You will go?
I'm cold, sir.
Cold?
Yes.
And standing in a pool.
Go then, Jane.
Go.
But he still retained my hand.
And I could not free it.
I bethought myself of an expedient.
I think I hear Mrs. Fairfax move, sir, said I.
Well, leave me.
He relaxed his fingers, and I was gone.
I regained my couch, but never thought of sleep.
Till morning dawn, I was tossed on a buoyant but unquiet
sea, where billows of trouble rolled under surges of joy.
I thought sometimes I saw beyond its wild
waters, ashore, sweet as the hills of Bueller.
And now and then a freshening gale, wakened by
hope, bore my spirit triumphantly towards the born.
But I could not reach it, even in fancy.
A counteracting breeze blew off land and continually drove me back.
Sense would resist delirium, judgment would warn passion.
Too feverish to rest, I rose as soon as day dawned.